how to prepare for the next pandemic
welcome to another true Health Tuesdays
and there has been some discussion about
this in Europe about what to do if there
was another pandemic we don't know when
that's going to be they call it disease
X because they don't really know when
that could be but they have a couple of
possibilities looking at what's going on
around the world things like Ebola zika
virus Etc and um what would we do in
that kind of a
situation so I to ask you basically what
should we do to be prepared and I think
things will probably go down a little
differently if we did have another
pandemic there was this article that was
published in the Washington Post titled
America shut down in response to co
would we ever do it again and the
authors of this paper would say no
actually there's going to be a lot of
resistance and tension if there's
anything like a public health mandate to
do it next time
which would definitely lead to an
acceleration of course of that
amplification of a potential contagious
virus we know that last time this
happened there were situations in
certain states where there was actually
rationing of healthcare which means that
there were so many people sick all at
the same time that it just overwhelmed
the healthcare industry and they could
not actually take care of patients and
basically what happened was the state
had to pass the uh protocols
specifically Health crisis protocols
which basically States at that point
that if you go to the hospital you
cannot expect to have the standard of
care because there's simply just not
enough Healthcare employees nurses
doctors oxygen medications to take care
of everybody all at the same time that
makes
sense well you may not know this but
this actually happened in
Idaho and it came close to happening in
a number of other states including the
one that I worked in which was
California so one of the things that
you've got to realize is that you may
not be able to depend on infrastructure
and Healthcare infrastructure in the
next
pandemic here's a publication here Idaho
activates crisis standards of care in
three Healthcare districts in Southern
Idaho and they simply go and talk about
what happened here this is the high
number of both clinical and non-al
clinical staff unable to work due to the
impacts of the virus infections coupled
with a nationwide Staffing shortage
limiting access to contracted traveling
staff is impacting current Hospital
operations it's also limiting the
availability of hospitals to maintain
capacity for things like intensive care
beds due to inadequate Staffing
additionally Nationwide shortages of
blood and blood products is
significantly impacting Health Care
Systems and most have implemented blood
conversion strategies or conservation
strategies so it's not just blood it's
not just Staffing we also see issues
with medications because a lot of the
medications that we use in the United
States come from overseas and have to be
shipped here the other thing that we saw
in the last pandemic here is the fact
that we may have the technology but if
we don't have the staff to deliver that
technology then it's not going to be
useful this was an example here where we
had dialysis machines but no dialysis
technologists or nurses to actually
administer the technology to
patients so in my estimation these are
the issues that we're going to be
dealing with in the next pandemic number
one lockdowns may not be as complete or
as long because people have gone through
that they know what the downsides of
lockdowns are in terms of businesses and
let's face it people's uh appreciation
for Authority is not the same as it was
in early 2020 and so because of all of
this surges may come earlier and perhaps
spread more rapidly and more quickly and
as a result of that there will be higher
demand for healthc care products and
services because people are going to get
sick
and I'm actually going somewhere with
this because we're going to have to
realize that we're going to have to be
able to have a plan B um so number two
there's going to be possible hoarding
and anticipated Health Products this is
for either personal use or resale we all
know about people that hoarded alcohol
um uh uh material so for hang cleansers
for instance even toilet paper all of
these things were hoarded so that they
could be sold on the black market for
very high price
there will be a shortage of supply of
healthcare products and the availability
of drugs will be low let's say there is
a drug that's off Lael that could be
used let's just say that that's a
possibility we don't know that that
would work because it could be a
different virus if that were felt to be
the case by the majority of people
obviously that medication would be
bought out sold out hoarded and would
not be available for everybody in the
United States there wouldn't be any
studies available on any specific drugs
as I mentioned though however if it was
it probably would not be available and
that's not only because of increased
demand but decreased supply which is
number three here supply chain may be
disrupted both domestically and
internationally uh many people that we
rely on to transport this material will
be either ill contagious or Dead items
that require a supply chain may not be
available uh what may be available will
increase in value uh because it'll be in
high demand uh so medications like
insulin blood thinner
these are not going to be available so
people are going to need these they may
get complications from not getting these
and this may exacerbate Healthcare
Systems if vaccines are developed uh
let's just say per chance that they're
able to develop somehow a vaccine or
have a vaccine prior for some sort of uh
virus it's going to be very difficult to
distribute uh because there's just not
going to be that infrastructure to
deliver it and there would be limited of
any testing at that point so this is
going to be a very interesting time and
also many Healthcare Personnel may not
be available again because either
they're ill contagious or dead
especially since the ones taking care of
these patients are going to be at Ground
Zero taking care of them and our highest
risk for actually getting infected and
again this could lead to additional
crisis protocols being put into place
like they were already in Idaho and if
things get really out of hand and spiral
out of control you could have impact on
law enforcement which could lead to
looting and uh revocation of personal
freedoms things of that nature so
remember that all of these things are
delicately interl and when things start
to go down people start to uh act in
ways that are just not predictable or
maybe perhaps are predictable so as a
result of that um ideally we would want
to have access to standard of care
medicine so not saying anything against
standard of Care Medicine I am an
intensive care physician I treat
patients every day with medications that
are life-saving when people get into
critical situations the need of
antibiotics vasopressors insulin all of
these are things that prevent the chain
of life from
breaking Obviously good health care um
but even more than that lifestyle is
going to make those links in the chain
stronger and better able to withstand
that but let's remember that all sorts
of things can happen even in people who
have great Lifestyles people can get
into car accidents people can have
intracerebral bleeds and these are
things that need Advanced Health Care
and if you don't have it then you get
bad outcome so ideally we would like to
have access to all of those standards of
care good medicine but realize that not
all these things are going to be
available especially in crisis
situations so that if you're dealing
with a pandemic you're going to want to
make sure that you have a plan B and
ideally a plan B would be something
that's not dependent on a supply chain
not dependent on a diagnosis or a test
not dependent on a pharmacist dispensing
it not being able to be hoarded and it
should be widely available and
inexpensive perhaps even free and
effective against a number of infectious
agents so let's talk about two of those
today one of them is going to be
sunlight and as you can see here
sunlight as we go through the number of
years up to the pandemic notice that
influenza is something that is very
common when the sun is the lowest in the
sky in fact a number of Studies have
shown that sunlight is very good at
preventing a lot of these illnesses in
fact if you look at the illnesses that
we keep track of things like heart
disease covid-19 stroke uh lower
respiratory diseases Alzheimer's disease
diabetes influenza pneumonia kidney
disease you can see that they all seem
to fluctuate with the seasons it may not
be uh you know humidity and temperature
although some people might make that
argument but I believe it's related to
the amount of sunlight that we are
actually getting and to that degree
there's been a number of studies that
have looked at this one study looked at
this in Europe to see when the covid-19
surges
started in the Autumn of 2020 and what
they found is when they looked at the
different countries in Europe they found
that temperature in these countries made
absolutely no prediction as to when
those countries were going to have their
surge the humidity again had no
predictive power in determining when
those surges started in the Autumn of
2020 but when you look at Latitude so
with Finland at the very top of the
globe and Greece at the bottom of Europe
you can see there was a very strong
correlation in terms of latitude
indicating that it was sunlight
particularly that was keeping people out
of the surges of covid-19 another study
looked at this uh in the United States
in Great Britain and in Italy and they
looked at mortality scores dependent on
the latitude and of course a lot of you
might think well vitamin D yeah that's
something that you get from the Sun and
that might be involved with this well
here here they looked at areas that were
not getting enough vitamin D in the
winter that couldn't because ultraviolet
B radiation which is the type of
radiation that stimulates vitamin D
production in the skin was not able to
come through at that angle however
ultraviolet a and of course infrared
light could do that and what they found
very significantly is when they
eliminated the portions of the United
States that could make enough vitamin D
in the winter and they just looked at
the portion of the United States that
couldn't they noticed a very specific
relationship that as the amount of
ultraviolet radiation went up that's
ultraviolet a radiation not the type of
radiation that makes vitamin D they
noticed that mortality from covid-19
went down they noticed exactly the same
relationship in England and the same
relationship in Italy and they came to a
very specific conclusion as a result of
this they said if if this is a causal
relationship it suggests that optimizing
sun exposure may be a possible Public
Health intervention given that the
effect appears independent of a vitamin
D pathway it suggests possible new co9
therapies well this was very interesting
of course and I teamed up with another
scholar by the name of Margaret scutch
who is A geographist from the University
of
Mexico and we looked at the same thing
and we found in a global situation
that countries that were higher in
Latitude than uh countries that were
closer to the L to the equator had worse
mortality had higher
mortality uh than those that were not
and so this is also something that we've
been finding as well so the question
might be why would that be the case why
would it be that sunlight might be
helpful not only for influenza but for
covid-19 and perhaps a myriad of other
viruses well it has to do with what's
going on in the cell in the cell there
is a prooxidant called at 2 or
Angiotensin 2 which gets converted to
Angiotensin 17 which is an antioxidant
that's a good conversion because you
want antioxidants and you want to get
rid of prooxidants well as it turns out
that is mitigated by an enzyme called A2
A2 of course is the enzyme that the SARS
K2 virus binds to and
inhibits so the prooxidant Angiotensin 2
actually is pro r or reactive oxygen
species we don't like reactive oxygen
species and cells normally and um as a
result of that the ace2 does something
very good in making Angiotensin 17
because angot tensin 17 actually blocks
reactive oxygen species which is good so
as you can see here very clearly from
this graph A2 is something that you want
to have unfortunately the virus hits it
it inhibits it and it also stimulates
white blood cells to make more reactive
oxygen species so what do we do is we
want to reduce the amount of oxygen
species because they can make blood
clots and those blood clots clog up the
pulmonary arteries and they can cause
hypoxemia so uh one way of mitigating
reactive oxygen species is to make sure
you're getting enough sleep at night so
going to bed early getting enough
melatonin from the pineal gland is going
to minimize reactive oxygen
species but a new study uh one that was
published in melatonin research by Scott
Zimmerman and Russell Ryder has shown
that in fact melatonin can be made on
site in the mitochondria by simple
exposure to the sun which gives quite
amount of near infrared radiation or
near infrared light and that will be
very very helpful we can see this in
terms of proof by looking at something
called plasma F2 isoprostane and as you
can see in covid patients they're always
higher regardless of the age group
meaning that covid does oxidative damage
on cells so this is something that we
really want to avoid if possible so
there was a public publication that was
published last year in actually in
2022 in one of the top photochemistry
and photobiology journals called the
Journal of photochemistry and
photobiology and what they did was a
cross uh basically a randomized placebo
control trial where they made them wear
this led vest these covid patients that
had come into the hospital and these LED
bulbs were not giving off light that you
could see but rather light that you
couldn't see in the near infrared field
and uh this actually showed a dramatic
Improvement in covid-19 outcomes in fact
these patients were discharged from the
hospital 4 days earlier when they were
given just 15 minutes a day of this type
of near infrared radiation what's really
interesting as well is that you can get
a huge amount of near infrared radiation
just by going outside in the sun but
particularly if you're in the sun around
trees with green leaves because as you
can see here the infrared radiation part
of the spectrum is amp Amplified going
from here to here if you're outside in
green spaces and so going outside in
green spaces is tremendously beneficial
in terms of the amount of near infrared
light so going outside into green spaces
into trees grass leaves is very
beneficial now this is something that
we've known for a long period of time
and you can see here these are pictures
of hospitals around the world that
utilized in their patient treatment
protocols well before the 1920s getting
out into the sun because they noticed
that these uh young people patients you
can see here that they've got them all
sort of lined up here uh this particular
one here is uh in Colorado I believe is
in Denver where these um these patients
are outside getting plenty of sunlight
now if you think that this is kind of
Fringe or maybe people don't understand
this well here is the Harvard Kennedy
School of
Business and they know that there's a
huge huge uh um impact of economic
problems when you have influenza in a
pandemic and so these two professors at
Harvard came up with this publication
looking at exactly this and they found
that sunlight was protective against
influence in fact in their abstract they
wrote this very strongly worded
statement we find that sunlight strongly
protects against getting influenza and
this relationship was driven almost
entirely by the severe H1N1 pandemic in
the fall of 2009 so just a recent
pandemic that we've seen so we've seen
here just looking at sunlight that it
does fit all of our criteria it's not
dependent on a supply chain it's not
dependent on a diagnosis or a test it's
not dependent on a pharmacist dispensing
it um it's not able to be hoarded you
can't hoard sunlight it's widely
available and inexpensive and it's
effective against a number of infectious
agents as we've seen uh of course
sometimes the clouds come in and you
can't get it all but eventually if you
wait long enough there will be enough
sunlight so I do think that that that is
beneficial okay let's talk about another
type of therapy which is hydrotherapy
and this encourages an innate immune
response there's two types to your
immune system there is the innate immune
system and there is the Adaptive immune
system and unfortunately the innate
immune system gets weaker with age and
it may be the reason why people who are
older in age had worse covid but as you
can see here there are certain aspects
of this innate immune system like the
macro maccrage the monoy and the natural
killer cells which are very Adept at
killing things that you've never seen
before from an immunological standpoint
the major player in that is something
called interferon interferon is a
substance that your body makes that has
a very broad coverage against many
different types of Invaders including
viruses now there was a paper that was
published way back in 2020 four years
ago that suggested based on evidence
that SARS K2 just like its ancestors
SARS and M
suppresses the body's ability to make
interferon it suppresses the innate
immune system and we could see that here
further on this was published in science
and it showed very specifically that
related to the amount of interferon that
was secreted in the body if there was a
large amount there was a mild amount or
mild reaction to covid-19 if very little
was made that was critical so as you can
see here the more interfer on your body
can make the better you are able to
weather the storm of covid-19 and this
went on and on and you can see here that
they actually delved into SARS CO2 and
actually found the specific Gene that
does this it's called Mac one and they
found that Mac one which is a gene in
SARS CO2 was required for your body to
suppress interferon so in other words
when this Gene was activated which it
always was in SARS K2 it was able to
suppress your body's ability to make
interferon and therefore gain a foothold
into your system and wreak havoc well
when scientists took this Gene and made
mutations in it basically made it
ineffective and then infected the body
with SARS K2 you can see here going from
Blue which was the wild type where Mac 1
is intact to the yellow where Mac 1 was
damaged you can see here that SARS kov 2
was no match for the body's interferon
levels you can see that interferon
levels were much higher with the mutated
SARS
K2 uh uh uh version and that in all of
these cases the body was able to mount
an immune response what does this mean
this means that Mac 1 or the virus the
gene Mac 1 on the virus SARS kov 2 is
imperative if SARS kov 2 wants to get a
foothold and the reason why that is is
because it
suppresses interferon secretion in the
body so understanding that and realizing
of course that you can't Simply
inactivate Mac 1 what you need to do is
you need to come up with ways that are
able to work around Mac one and
stimulate interferent levels regardless
and that's exactly what we're going to
talk about here so we found in many
studies going back that
interferon in chronic viral infections
actually was able to to basically uh
reduce a chronic infection and even even
cure them uh these were a bunch of covid
patients that were given interferon just
subcutaneously and what we found is that
it
reduced the hospitalization rates in
these patients by
50% so what can we do is there a natural
way of increasing interferon levels well
actually it turns out the answer is yes
and this was published many years ago in
this study that was titled hypothermia
in humans enhances interferon gamma
synthesis and Alters the peripheral lymy
population
guess what when you heated up the body
to around 39° C or 102° F there was a
10-fold increase in the amount of
interferon that was secreted so not only
not giving Tylenol or paracetamol to
patients with fevers to make sure that
their fevers are adequate unless of
course they go over 103 or 104 or they
have a rapid heart rate or seizures you
don't want that but so long as they're
having a healthy fever during an
infection this is actually beneficial
because because interferon is the way
that the body gets rid of those viral
particles and as you can see this was
also practiced many years ago you can
see this is a photograph from the Battle
Creek sanitarium patient in a world bath
this is around 1910 well before the
discovery of penicillin this is how we
used to stimulate the body's inate
immune system to make interferon there's
another picture here of light going back
to our first uh picture there basically
but you can see it's very labor
intensive it requires human labor
to get these people's uh temperatures up
high enough uh there was an article back
in
1919 juring the epidemic of influenza
written by a physician by the name of
Wells a rubble who went on to be the
first president of what is now known as
Loma Linda University and he said that
the present epidemic of influenza has
furnished an excellent opportunity to
test out the efficacy of rational
treatment in dealing with respiratory
disorders especially in conditions
accompanying and following ATT acts of
influenza and he compared what was going
on in the Army hospitals at the time
that was using a lot of aspirin which
actually brings fevers down compared to
what they were doing in the Northeast in
about 10 sanitariums and you can see
here that when early on that fevers were
encouraged rather than being suppressed
there was one
eth the incidence of pneumonia and of
course pneumonia at the time was a
killer because this was before
antibiotics and once you had pneumonia
there wasn't much that you can do
overall however you can see that the use
of hydrotherapy to increase body
temperature reduced the infection
fatality rate by almost
one6 there's also other stories where an
entire seminary in Hutchinson Minnesota
was affected and not a single student
was lost because they quickly employed
the use of hydrotherapy among other
things that we'll talk about so this was
not done in a vacuum there was actually
some research at the time uh back in
1917 by a gentleman by the name of
Wagner yorg who was a Austrian
psychiatrist who noticed that in his San
Asylum patients that those that had
neurosyphilis actually improved their
symptoms when they had fever so as you
can see here in this picture uh Dr
Wagner ureg who's the gentleman there in
the back with his hand on the shoulder
of the patient as this patient is being
injected with malaria infected blood
from another patient with a similar
blood type to induce malaria in that
patient now that patient would have high
fevers and those high fevers would then
stimulate the innate immune system to
kill the infection that was chronically
going on in this patient well for his
work he won Dr Wagner yorg won the Nobel
Prize in medicine in 1927 and that was
work from a decade earlier in
1917 well interestingly the very next
year in
1928 we had the discovery of penicillin
and that he for
that Fleming won the Nobel Prize in 1945
now it's interesting to note that it's
much easier to purify a substance like
penicillin and to give it out to
patients and uh much less work intensive
um but also very uh effective so the
problem however though is during a
pandemic which is what we're talking
about it might be very difficult to
process process purify and manufacture
enough of a drug that would take care of
a patient in a pandemic just because of
the simple numbers so instead of going
back to nothing and just going home and
waiting to be admitted because you're
hypoxic let's go back to the step right
before that which would include
hydrotherapy so hydrotherapy again is
not dependent on a supply chain it's not
dependent on a diagnosis or a test it
wouldn't be dependent on a pharmacist
dispensing it would not be able to be
hoarded it's widely available and
inexpensive perhaps even free all you
need is some water and some towels and
it's effective against a number of
infectious agents that we just talked
about and that's because it works to
increase interferon which is the body's
own system that is used and utilized to
attack a number of different diseases
all right so we talked about sunshine
and hydrotherapy all of this in addition
to other types of care like
Nutrition By the way there are some
studies that show that plant-based diets
improve and increase interferon uh
secretion and that the inate immune
system is Amplified by a plantbased diet
so being vegan basically they also note
by the way that a low carb ketogenic
diet which would you which would occur
if you don't eat that third meal of the
day and instead intermittently fast that
increases the Adaptive immune system
which uses antibodies to specific
antigens but also realize that exercise
getting plenty of sleep as we talked
about in fresh air which contains uh
phyto Tides from trees can also help and
improve your uh longevity during a
pandemic because all of these things are
not dependent on a supply chain not
dependent on a diagnosis or test not
dependent on pharmacist dispensing it
not able to be hoarded widely available
and inexpensive and effective against a
number of infectious agents so I would
like to say here and just stop that um
again let me be very clear I'm not
saying that these things should be done
instead of standard of care but rather
in addition to and as a plan B there's
no harm in in implementing these things
anyway of course if things go AR and
medications are needed in extreme
situations they they may be always there
but remember and this is the key Point
here this is the underlying basis of
this entire thing is that if more and
more people were to Institute what we're
talking about here there would be less
and less people that would be dependent
and require the um the systems that are
set up in the healthcare
uh and so they would may be used for
people that actually would need them and
where these things perhaps would not be
able to treat 100% let's not forget that
there was still a case fatality rate
even with hydrotherapy although it was
one sixth of that and can you imagine if
we had a situation where only one six of
the people needing Health Care um
products needed it instead of all of
them we would actually have enough and
we'd be able to treat more and more
people so I hope this has been uh
important uh I hope this has been
helpful to you and I think you should
look at more of these things as we um
look to the Future in terms of making
ourselves more healthy and more
resilient to these things that come in
our environment thanks for joining us
again for True Health
Tuesdays